Charlie!
查理
I wasn't so sure you'd be on the bus
我擔心你趕不上這班巴士
Didn't want your white brothers thinking
不想讓你的白人弟兄們誤以為
you were the best we had
你是我們族堻抸u秀的人才
SOLOMON ISLANDS
「所羅門群島1943年」
Watch out!
小心!
My hand!
我的手!
Goddamn!
他媽的!
We're running out of ammo. We gotta get out of here
快沒子彈了 我們得快走
Move!
前進!
Come on!
過來!
Come on, you can do it! Come on!
過來,你辦得到的!
We got nothin', Enders! We're out of ammo!
完全沒彈藥了,恩得斯! 我們沒彈藥了!
Joe¡­ Nobody else needs to die. We can go! We can get outta here!
喬伊,我們不該再平白犧牲 現在撤退還來得及!
We got orders!
我們身負任務!
They told us to hold the position! And that's what we're gonna do!
上面要我們守住這個點! 我們就得死守在這!
Get up, marine! Hold the goddamn position!
起來,阿兵哥! 死守下去!
Come on!
拼啦!
Get down!
趴下!
Tommy
湯米
Goddamn you!
該死的傢伙!
Oh, no! No!
不!
- Bill! - I'm out
-比爾! -我沒子彈了
Come on! Come on!
過來!
Goddamn you, Joe Enders
你他媽的,喬伊恩得斯!
No¡­ No!
不!
Raise your right hand
右手舉起來
- I¡­ State your full name¡­ - I, Ben Yahzee¡­
-我…說自己的名字… -我,班亞吉…
CAMP PENDLETON, CALIFORNIA
彭德爾頓營,加利福尼亞
..do solemnly swear to support and defend the constitution of the US¡­
茲誓言支持並保護美國憲法
..against all enemies, foreign and domestic¡­ ..against all enemies, foreign and domestic¡­
抵禦任何敵人 不論國內或國外…
Jap Ha-Go. Who can give me the code word for ¡°tank¡±?
日本人稱之為「箱子」 誰知道「坦克」的密碼?
Come on. You boys wanna be codetalkers
你們想成為密碼戰士
Show me some brains. Think!
那就要有腦袋啊,快想!
What do we call a tank?
我們怎麼說坦克?
Chay-da-gahi
Chay-da-gahi
Tortoise. Good
烏龜,很好
Artillery. Code word?
大炮,密碼?
In code. Private Whitehorse
請說密碼,白馬二等兵
Be-al-doh-tso-lani?
Be-al-doh-tso-lani?
Very good
很好
Japanese Zero. Code word?
日本零式戰機,密碼?
KANEOHE BAY US NAVAL HOSPITAL
「肯尼歐灣美國海軍醫院 1943」
We can go! We can get outta here!
現在撤退還來得及!
They told us to hold the position!
上面要我們守住這個點!
Nice day, huh?
天氣真好啊
Joe?
喬伊?
Didn't hear a word, did you?
你根本沒聽到 我在說話,對吧?
That's what happens to a man when he's talking to a beautiful woman
男人碰到美女不都是這樣
It happens when you're not watching my lips, Joe
你不讀我的唇語才會這樣
Watch this
你看我
You're a mess, Joe. You're not fooling anybody
你還沒康復,騙不了人的
No, Rita. He's a mess
不,麗塔,他才是還沒康復
I'm getting better every day
我每天都在康復中
You got a perforated eardrum, Enders. Your equilibrium's all screwy
你中耳破損,平衡感不正常
You can't go back to war if you can't stand up
站都站不起來怎麼重回戰場
Let's go, marines. This war ain't gonna wait forever. Let's go
走吧,勝利不會從天上掉下來
Joe¡­
喬伊?
Why don't you just stay here, Joe?
為什麼你不好好留下來?
Somebody's gotta keep the WAVES company
總得有人留下來陪婦女救護團
Are you gonna help me or not?
你到底幫不幫我?
Marked improvement
改善很多了
And his left ear is the worse of the two?
他左耳情況比較差嗎?
It's¡­ amazing
好得真快
TBY hasn't got the range of the TBX
TBY型的範圍比不上TBX
So you may need a relay to get your transmission to command post
所以訊號可能要分程傳遞
But what it really comes down to is speed and accuracy under pressure
但重點是壓力下的速度與精準
Transcribe now
開始解讀
Victor, Victor. This is X-ray. Over
維多,這堿OX光,完畢
Damn it! We got a unit under fire!
可惡!我方弟兄遭炮火攻擊!
We're losing men
傷亡慘重
I need this message decrypted
請解讀這段訊息
¡°Request fire support. We have target at one-one-niner, Baker one-five.¡±
「請求炮火支援, 目標在119,B15」
¡°Pillbox with heavy machine gun. Fire at will.¡±
「碉堡有重機槍 請立刻開火」
Beginner's luck
初學者手氣好
You're up, mac
換你了,大哥
- Corporal Enders reporting, sir. - At ease
-恩得斯下士報到,長官 -稍息
You've done well as a marine, Corporal
你的表現相當不錯,下士
Better than you did as a civilian
比從軍前的行為好多了
Stole a motorbike, crashed it. Got kicked out of high school
偷竊撞毀機車 遭高中勒令退學
Assault and battery¡­ on one Father Crispin O'Donnell?
襲擊並毆打克婸姨畯蟫朘咫
A priest?
連教士都打?
Assistant principal at Archbishop Keenan High School, sir, and head disciplinarian
他是齊納主教高中副校長 兼訓導主任
Public-school boy myself
我以前念的是公立學校
Some minor problems in boot
訓練中心時還是小錯不斷
A commendation for valor in Shanghai
在上海獲頒最佳勇氣獎
And you made a hell of a stand on the Solomons
死守所羅門群島表現傑出
Tough bit of business there, huh?
那兒很苦吧?
Pretty tough, sir
相當艱苦,長官
But you're prepared to jump right back into it?
可是,你想再回去?
Yes, sir. Very much so
是的,長官,非常想
Very much so
非常想
Well¡­
可是…
The Japs have pretty much busted every code we've thrown at 'em, Corporal
我們的密碼全遭日軍破解
You men on the Solomons were lost to a broken code
你在所羅門群島的弟兄 因密碼被破解全部陣亡
Tell me something. You ever run into any Indians on the Solomons?
在所羅門碰到過印地安人嗎?
- Indians, sir? - Navajo, to be exact
-印地安人,長官? -正確的說,應該是納瓦荷人
The Corps has developed a new code based on their language
軍方用他們的語言 發展出一套新密碼
It's had quite an impact
評價相當不錯
So much so the navy have decided to go to great lengths to protect it
所以海軍總部下令全力保護它
That's why you're here
這就是找你來的原因
You're to pair with one of them, keep his ass safe
你將與密碼戰士配對 全力保護他們
Your job is to keep him alive so he can do his job
你負責保護他們的性命 以利他們執行密碼任務
Begging the major's pardon, but I believe I'd best serve the Corps killing Japs
抱歉,我的專長是屠殺日軍
not baby-sitting some Indian
不是照顧印地安人
Enders, we didn't pick your name out of a hat
我們不是隨便挑到你的
We need good marines
我們需要的是傑出陸戰隊員
That's why you're standing here
所以才選上你
Take a look
你看
It's a Navajo. Or it was
他就是個納瓦荷人…應該死了
Tortured to death by Japanese intelligence trying to bust our code
遭日軍逼問密碼 嚴刑拷打致死
Fortunately, he couldn't help them even if he wanted to
所幸,他想說也說不出所以然
- Sir? - Man's a Navajo, not a codetalker
-長官? -他是納瓦荷人但不是密碼戰士
Code's based on their language, but it is still a code
密碼由他們的語言編成 但畢竟還是密碼
Tojo would like nothing more than to catch a live one
東條巴不得活捉一個密碼戰士
What I'm about to tell you, Corporal, cannot leave this room
我以下的話,絕不能洩漏出去
Under no circumstances can you allow your codetalker to fall into enemy hands
不管在任何情況下 密碼戰士絕不能落入敵人手中
Your mission is to protect the code¡­
你的任務是保護密碼
at all costs
不惜任何代價
You understand me?
懂我的意思嗎?
Yes, sir, I do
是的,長官,我懂
Good
很好
Congratulations. You just made sergeant
恭喜你,你剛獲升中士
Keep those hands vertical
手臂保持垂直
Way to go, marine
不錯,阿兵哥
Fortino, take over
佛第諾,接替我一下
Hey¡­ That was you, right, sitting in front of the major's office?
少校辦公室外的是你,對吧?
Yeah. Listen, I'm Pete Henderson
我叫彼得韓德森
They call me Ox. Not cos of my big muscles or anything
他們叫我公牛 不是因為我的肌肉
I'm from Oxnard, California. Just north of Hollywood a ways
是因為我住在加州公牛城 好萊塢北邊一點點
So you're with JASCO too, huh?
你也是兩棲作戰通訊連的人?
Hey, know where we might find 2nd Joint Assault Signal?
請問兩棲通訊二分隊怎麼走?
No fuckin' idea, mac
沒聽說過,老土
Thanks. Thanks a bunch
多謝
I've never seen so many white men
從沒看過那麼多白人
They've never seen so many Navajo
他們也沒看過那麼多納瓦荷人
Looks to me like you got to see a little action there
看起來你上過戰場
Me too
我也是
Jap sons of bitches shot me right in the ass
屁股挨了日本鬼子的子彈
You believe that shit? I wasn't running or nothin'
相不相信? 並不是我想逃避上前線
So, your duty with JASCO have anything to do with these Navajo radiomen?
你在兩棲通訊的任務 跟這些納瓦荷通信兵有關嗎?
I'm not at liberty to say
我奉命守密
I see you got a new stripe there. Me too
我發現你陞官了,我也是
So I'm guessing the orders you can't tell me are the same orders I can't tell you
我猜,你不能說的秘密 跟我不能說的是一樣
Hell of a thing, huh?
了不起的任務吧?
Ain't a democracy, Sergeant. It's the marines
身不由己,中士,這堿O軍隊
They look pretty normal, I guess
他們看起來蠻正常的
Expecting them to wear war paint?
難道他們得噴上迷彩?
Maybe we ought to go introduce ourselves. They look a little lost to me
或許該過去打個招呼 他們好像迷路了
Henderson
韓德森
I wouldn't get too friendly
我不想跟他們太親近
How!
怎麼樣?
Just kiddin'. I'm Ox
開個玩笑,我叫公牛
Whitehorse
我叫白馬
This is Yahzee. Ben
他姓亞吉,叫班
- Next. - Beautiful. Beautiful
-下一位 -漂亮
Close your eyes. It'll taste better. Who's next?
閉著眼睛會比較好吃 下一個是誰?
Mind if I join you?
可以一起吃嗎?
I'm Ben Yahzee. Guess the Corps paired us up
我叫班亞吉,跟你同一組
How you doin'?
你好嗎?
You're blocking my view
你擋住我的視線了
Oh, sorry
對不起
What do they call this crap anyway?
這難吃的東西是什麼?
Marines call it chow
軍方稱之為食物
Well, there's a propaganda effort
有廣告不實的嫌疑哦
Sorry. You can have mine
對不起,我的賠你
Shit
啊,糟糕
What'd you say your name was again, Private?
你說你叫什麼名字,二等兵?
It's Yahzee. Ben Yahzee
我叫班亞吉
Hold this
端著
Shit
可惡
How's your white man?
你的白人搭檔怎麼樣？
Hungry
飢餓
I'm in for a couple more
我再玩幾把
You writing to your son?
寫信給你兒子？
Tell him I say hello
幫我問個好
Pair of cowboys for Big E
大恩先生K一對
- Possible straight for the Greek. - Possible thumb up the Greek's ass
-希臘人可能是順子 -可能是一手烏龍啦
Oh, a pair of twos for the kid. Lookin' good
小伙子2一對,有前途
- Oh, come on! - Now there's a bold move
有人膽子不小
All right
好啦
OK¡­ Oh, another mess for the Sunshine State
佛州小子陷入兩難
- What, are you mad at me? - Just want your money
-你對我不爽? -我只是想贏你的錢
Hey! Look at that. A trio of nines. Pretty
9三條!漂亮
- You shuffle that deck? - I certainly did
-你牌到底有沒有洗? -當然有
Nines bets. I'll raise it two bits
9喊,我加兩毛五
Call
我跟
We all got thumbs up our asses
我們都是一手爛牌
You won't for much longer. I got a buddy in Intel that says we ship out in a week
玩不久了,我朋友在軍機處 他說我們下周開拔
I been hearing ¡°next week¡± for a month
「下周」已經說一個月了
I didn't know you knew anybody in Intelligence, Harri
我不知道你有朋友在軍機處
Next year'd be all right with me
拖到明年我也無所謂
Gentlemen, read 'em and weep. Look at that. Nines and fours
各位,哭吧,9帶4
Full boat, baby
葫蘆
Cowboys over queens. Read 'em and die
K帶Q葫蘆,哭死你
Oh, Jesus!
這怎麼可能!
- Fuck it. I'm out. - Yeah. I'm gonna go write the missus
-我不玩了 -我要去寫信給老婆
God knows what a girlwill do without reassurance
天知道女人收不到音訊會幹嘛
Son of a bitch
爛角
Hey, looks like we got a coupla seats opening up. You wanna come join us?
有空位了,一起玩嗎?
Are you serious?
你開玩笑的吧?
What, Injun poker? Hey, how do you boys do that again?
紅番撲克?你們怎麼玩?
Card on the head, only fool can't see it is you
牌放在頭上,白癡都一目瞭然
You want to come on over, or what?
到底要不要過來坐?
Cut me in
算我一份
I'm thinkin' Fiery Cross, high-low, hoggers OK, ace plays both ways¡­
我想玩大小通吃 最大最小都贏,A可以當兩頭
Hey, don't let him scare you
別被他唬住
If you've ever played a high-low game, it's like any other. Waste of time and money
反正就是大小通吃 了不起浪費時間跟金錢
Well, ante up¡­ Chief
出底錢,酋長
How'd you know I was a chief?
你怎麼知道我是酋長?
You must've seen me showering with my war bonnet
你一定看過我戴著戰帽洗澡
- Deal 'em up, deal 'em up. - You know, we don't take wampum here
-發牌 -我們可不收貝殼串
Beautiful
真好聽
All right, then
聽好了,各位
Orders finally came through
命令終於下來了
We ship out tomorrow morning
我們明天早上出航
Destination: the island of Saipan
目的地：塞班島
which is one of the stepping stones we gotta take on our road show to Tokyo
它是我們通往東京的跳板
It's of strategic importance that we capture this island
攻下這個島極具戰略價值
We can get ourselves an advanced naval base
可以成立海軍前進基地
and an airstrip to land and refuel B-29's
和空軍跑道 以便B29降落和加油
and get our bombers within range of Tokyo
那麼東京就在轟炸航程內了
Now, Saipan is Japanese soil, and there's 30,000 of 'em dug in
目前塞班島是日本的領土 上面駐守有三萬日軍
They're gonna fight for every square inch
他們必然會死守到底
because it's their home, but we're gonna take it away from 'em!
因為那是他們的家 但我們要把它搶過來!
Yeah! Kill me some Japs!
殺日本鬼子!
We're gonna be in front of the whole damn division
我們是整個師的先頭部隊
We're gonna be the eyes and the ears
我們是全師的耳目
We're gonna be sniffin' out enemy positions
我們要聞出敵軍的所在地點
coordinating the naval gunfire -
協調海軍炮火
exactly what we've been training to do for the last four months. All right?
任務跟四個月來的訓練一樣 沒問題吧?
Now, we got some new radiomen from headquarters
司令部派來了幾位通信兵
There's a Private Whitehorse¡­
二等兵白馬
and Yahzee¡­
和亞吉
and a couple of sergeants, Enders and Henderson
以及兩位中士 恩得斯和韓德森
who, if I'm understanding these orders correctly
他們…依據命令…
will be covering our Navajos' asses
將掩護我們的納瓦荷戰士
Goddamn you, Joe Enders!
你他媽的,喬伊恩得斯!
..but I'm tellin' you, we'll be steppin' into our share of the shit nonetheless
現在輪到我們赴湯蹈火了
Any questions?
有問題嗎?
Sounds like you're dying
聽起來你好像快掛了
These might help get rid of the taste
這可以幫你消除氣味
Charlie and I, we both lost it on the boat ride from San Diego
查理和我從聖地牙哥坐船來時 也吐得死去活來
Not many bodies of water in Arizona
亞歷桑那有水的地方並不多
Life Savers really helped
口氣清香糖還蠻有用的
You want a Life Saver?
要不要來一個?
What are you doin' here?
你為什麼來這?
Just trying to help
想幫個小忙罷了
Not what I meant
我不是這個意思
You mean what am I doing in this uniform?
你是說,我為什麼從軍?
It's my war too, Sergeant
戰爭也跟我有關啊,中士
I'm fighting for my country, for my land, for my people
為我的國家、土地、同胞而戰
Not your people I'm worried about
我擔心的倒不是你的同胞
Listen, Enders, I'm a codetalker
恩得斯,我是個密碼戰士
It takes me two-and-a-half minutes to do what used to take an hour
我只要二分半鍾就可以解讀 一般人一小時才懂的東西
Now, somebody wearing a lot more stripes than you
有位官階比你高很多的人
thinks that's worth something
認為這東西很有價值
Remind me to time you when you got bullets flying over your head
子彈飛到頭上時 記得叫我幫你計時
What the hell's wrong with you?
你到底是哪堣ㄟ矽?
From the halls of Montezuma
從蒙特祖瑪聖殿
To the shores of Tripoli
到屈波堮岸
We will fight our country's battles
我們為祖國而戰
On the land and on the sea
從陸地打到海上
First to fight for right and freedom
主要為權利和自由而戰
And to keep our honor clean
也為保衛我們的榮譽
We are proud to claim the title
我們為自己感到驕傲
Of United States Marines
我們是美國海軍陸戰隊
Hi
嗨
How's that ear?
耳朵怎麼樣?
Not that you'd ever admit it, but if it starts aching, take a couple of those
不管怎樣,痛時記得吃兩顆藥
And call me in the morning
第二天早上再打電話給我
You're not gonna be here in the morning, are you?
明早你就不在這了吧?
Shipping out without even buying me a drink
要走了也不請我喝一杯
Ought to be ashamed of yourself, hustling a¡­ hustling marines
騷擾軍人,你害不害羞?
What's your poison?
你愛喝什麼?
Jeez, might as well go all out. I'll get a shot of something
喲,我可能會熱情奔放哦 隨便都好
Rum
蘭姆吧
Eddie, give me a shot of Bacardi
艾迪,來杯巴卡迪
Make that two
兩杯
May as well join me, huh?
陪我一起喝嘛
- Why not? - OK
好啊
Thank you
謝謝
Well¡­ to war
敬這場戰爭
THE JAPANESE ISLAND OF SAIPAN JUNE 16, 1944
「1944年6月16日本塞班島」
Let's go, let's go, let's go!
快,快,快!
Get those men spread out!
叫他們散開!
Charlie, come on, come on, come on!
查理,快!
Come on, keep up!
跟上!
Let's go, let's go, let's go! Come on!
繼續走!加油!
- How am I doin'? - You're good
-我怎麼樣? -非常優秀
Let's go!
繼續前進!
Stay on my ass
跟緊一點
I told you to stay on my ass!
我叫你跟緊一點!
- Stay low! - Get out of there!
-蹲低一點! -出來!
Go!
沖!
Get him outta there!
救他出來!
- Hold still, damn it! - Get him outta there!
-不要動,可惡! -救他出來!
You sons of bitches!
你們這些王八蛋!
Fortino! Cover me!
佛第諾,掩護我!
Whitehorse, get down!
白馬,趴下!
Get down!
趴下!
Pappas!
帕帕斯!
Corpsman!
救護兵!
Helmet goes on your head! Corpsman!
鋼盔是戴在頭上的! 救護兵!
Take care of him
看看他的狀況
Put a hand on this
手壓住這!
Tank! Tank! Tank!
坦克!坦克!
You ready? Go! Go!
準備好了嗎?丟!
Harrigan, light it up!
哈利根,燒它個雞飛狗跳!
Let's go, boys! Keep up the fight!
前進,繼續加油
Are you hit? Are you hit?
你有中彈嗎?
You're OK. You're good, you're good
你沒事,你很好
- Are you OK, Chick? - Still in the hunt, Gunny
-你還好吧,奇克? -還能殺人,吉尼
- Harri? - You ain't gettin' rid of me that easy
-哈利? -想幹掉我沒那麼容易!
- Stay low! - Nellie? Pappas?
-趴低一點! -奈!帕帕斯!
Yeah, we're good
我們很好
Greek's predisposed to hyperventilate
希臘人有過度換氣徵兆
What?
什麼?
I can't breathe when I get excited
一興奮我就喘不過氣來
Goddamn! Must be hell on your gal!
干!那你女朋友可累了!
Enders, get the navy on the horn and tell 'em to dig out those guns
恩得斯,通知海軍 轟掉他們的炮陣地
Target reference¡­ dog one¡­
目標座標,D1
right 700
右700米
Elevation zero-five-zero
海拔050
Relay the damn coordinates!
把座標傳出去!
Arizona! Arizona!
亞歷桑那!亞歷桑那!
USS CALIFORNIA
「美國海軍加利佛尼亞號」
It sounds like they're underwater. Is it English?
好像水底傳來的，是英語嗎？
Target reference, dog one
目標座標,D1
south 700, elevation zero-five-zero
南700米,海拔050
Right 200!
右200米!
Up 50. Fire for effect
高50!立刻開火!
Let's go!
前進!
Move!
走!
Harrigan!
哈利根!
Torch the box!
火攻碉堡!
Kill him!
幹掉他!
Goddamn it!
王八蛋!
Shit
干
Nellie. Take the satchel charge
奈,炸藥包帶著!
You hear me? Move!
聽到了沒?快!
You're gonna cover me, right?
你會掩護我吧?
I'll go with you. We flank left
我一起去,從左翼進攻
I'll cover you. Smoke and cover
我掩護你們,煙幕彈
I can do this
我辦得到
Smoke 'em up!
投擲煙幕彈!
Cover up
掩護他!
Shit!
操!
Shit. Goddamn Nipponese touchdown!
操,日本隊被達陣了!
Heads up around 0500
0500時提高警覺
You're going to have replacements and ammo coming up. Over
補給品和彈藥會送過去，完畢
Roger. Make sure they have the new password
收到，請確認新口令
Challenge: ¡°Wind.¡± Answer: ¡°Talkers.¡±
問「獵風」，答「戰士」
That's what one of our Navajo brothers calls us
一位納瓦荷弟兄取的名字
What do you think? Over
覺得怎麼樣？完畢
¡°Windtalkers,¡± I like it.
「獵風戰士」我喜歡
OK, Kemo Sabe, keep your butts down tonight. Over
好拉，老友，一夜平安，完畢
Biscuits? How can you ruin biscuits?
這口糧真難吃
You are a whiny son of a bitch right now, aren't you?
你還真他媽愛抱怨
2200 hours in jungle hell - what does that make it on the East Coast?
塞班晚上10點,東岸幾點?
How the fucking hell should I know?
我怎麼會知道
Just seven¡­
7點…
It's 8am, Sunday morning
星期日早上8點
I hope my side of the bed didn't get taken up Saturday night
希望我的床昨晚沒被篡位
Nell, you'll give yourself an ulcer, you keep worrying about her
這麼不放心她,遲早胃潰瘍
Might get my ass sent back to Rhody, though
這樣我就可以回羅德島了
There's plenty of dollies outside of Rhode Island, Nell. Many plenty
羅德島辣妹不少哦
- Well, there sure as shit ain't any here. - Ain't that the truth
-這堛眯w沒半個 -這還用說
That's cos they're all in Daytona Beach. The most beautiful women in the world
她們全擠在德通海灘 世界上最美的女人
This one time, before the war
戰前有一次
I'm lyin' on the beach and this sweet little thing named Molly comes out the water
我躺在沙灘上,有個美女… 叫茉莉,從水堣W岸來
She walks straight up to me and asks me if I'm hungry¡­
走到我身邊,問我餓不餓
cos she's havin' a weenie roast
因為她只吃條小熱狗
Shit! Damn
哇靠!
Yeah, me and Molly, oh boy
於是我和茉莉…爽
Now I'm on Saipan with this giant Zippo strapped to my back
現在卻困在塞班島上 身上背個巨無霸打火機
and I'm roastin' human beings
專門烤人肉
Why I volunteered¡­ beyond me
為什麼會自願從軍 我實在搞不懂
Damn, I'm proud to be here
我倒是覺得蠻驕傲的
My whole family's been in the Corps
我全家都是海軍陸戰隊
My old man, he's a lifer
老爸是終身職
An ass-kicker on the land and on the sea
海上陸上都不可一世
Around the house too
在家一樣作威作福
Maybe now he'll back off
現在可能收斂點了
Pappas, I¡­
帕帕斯
I want you to do me a favor
希望你能幫個忙
If anything should happen to me
萬一我出了事
you make sure that my wife gets this
這個請交給我太太
I mean, she picked them out and all
這是她親手挑的
Don't talk like that, Nell
不要說這種話,奈爾
You don't even joke about shit like that
連玩笑都不要開
Now you put that ring back on. You're goin' home
戴回去,你會平安回家
Don't thank me till you've tried it
喝過才謝我還不遲
You missed mailcall
發信時你不在
What the hell are they doin'?
他們在幹嘛?
I don't know. They've been doin' it since sundown
不知道,日落後就忙個不停
Sounds like some kind of prayer
聽起來像是祈禱
Maybe they know our orders
或許他們知道我們的命令
Think you could do it, Joe?
你下得了手嗎,喬伊?
Give it a rest, Henderson
不要一直想這問題,韓德森
Give it a rest? I keep tryin', but¡­
不要想?我試過,可是…
I'm here to kill Japs, not marines
該殺的是日本人,不是自己人
I saw you a warrior, Yahzee¡­
你是個勇士，亞吉
You will make your family proud
你是家族的榮耀
What the hell you think you're doin', boy?
你在幹嘛,老弟?
Getting on my uniform
正要穿上制服
You know the difference between you and a Jap, Yahzee?
知道你跟日本人 有什麼差別嗎?
It's that uniform
差在制服
That's it
僅此而已
See, I know you people
我瞭解你們這些人
I know what kind of slanty-eyed savage you are, boy
我清楚你們這些鳳眼野蠻人
You ought to be careful out here all alone
落單時當心一點
No baby-sitter
沒有人照顧你時
I might just take you for a Jap
我可能會把你看成日本鬼子
You gonna let me get dressed, Chick?
你要讓我穿衣服嗎,奇克?
Or keep demonstrating what an ignorant fool you are?
還是繼續演無知的白癡?
How's that for an ignorant fool?
無知的白癡是吧?
Go ahead, try again
拿啊,你試試看
You gonna do somethin'?
你不是想幹什麼嗎?
Chick! Come on!
奇克,住手
Get off me!
走開!
- You OK, Ben? - Yeah
-你沒事吧,班? -沒事
Ben? Shit
班?噁心
I thought he was a Jap. You know, killed some marine for that uniform
我以為他是日本人 殺我弟兄,偷穿制服
Sure you did, Chick
再扯嘛,奇克
Damn Injun looks just like a Jap, don't he?
死紅番不像日本鬼子嗎?
Look, I'm no damn Injun
我不是死紅番
I'm Navajo, of the Bitter Water People, born for the Towering House clan
我是納瓦荷人 母系是苦水族,父系是塔樓族
But you do look like a Nip
但長相蠻像日本人
Next time you decide to take a bath, Private, let me know, or I'll kick your ass
下次要洗澡先通知我 否則我踢你屁股
Fuckin' shitbird
媽的敗類
Supposed to be with a baby-sitter all the time, I thought
他隨時都需要人照顧
Out here huntin' salmon and shit
連出去打魚時也一樣
That ceremony you saw last night? It's called a protection ceremony
昨晚你看到的是 我們的庇護儀式
Navajo believe, untila body's given a proper burial, the spirits stay near it
納瓦荷人相信屍體未安葬前 靈魂會一直待在附近
Chindis - that's what we call evilspirits. Demons
我們稱惡靈為僊邸司
I haven't thought much about it since I was a kid
我從小不曾認真想過這問題
Till I saw those dead bodies
直到我目睹這些死屍
You telling me you saw ghosts, Private?
你是說你看得到鬼魂?
No, Sergeant. I'm telling you I won't freeze up again
不,我是說我不再害怕了
Because your buddy smeared ash on your forehead?
因為你朋友在你額頭上抹灰?
That's right. Cos my buddy smeared ash on my forehead
沒錯,因為我朋友 在我額頭上抹灰
You ever see ghosts?
你看過鬼嗎?
No more stupid questions today, Private. That's an order
不要再問傻問題了 這是命令
Sounds beautiful
真好聽
You, uh, you self-taught?
無師自通嗎?
My dad was always playing
我爸爸常吹
You know what they say: if you can't beat 'em¡­
他們不是說「拼不過他就…」
No shit. My dad, he¡­ he gave me this thing
正確,這是我爸送我的
Used to call me the Pied Piper of the Pigs
他以前叫我小豬魔笛
Used to bring 'em in for feeding with this little tune I played
我一吹它們就過來吃飼料
I know I ain't gonna get you to quit playin' that thing, so¡­
我知道你不會停止吹笛子
like you just said, if you can't beat 'em¡­
所以「拼不過他就…」
I don't think it's gonna work
我覺得聲音不協調
Well, we ain't got much else to do out here. What the hell?
反正別無他法,管他的
OK
好吧
All right, you lead off. I'll follow you
你起音,我來和
2nd Recon Company will move out at 0600
第二偵查隊0600出發
and scout along road 04
沿四號路搜索下去
You can expect light resistance northwest of the palm grove. Over
椰林西北邊可能遭到輕微抵抗
Roger. What do you mean, light? No resistance is light! Over
收到，何謂「輕微」？ 沒有任何抵抗是輕微的，完畢
Remember, marine, Ours is not to question why,
記住座右銘不問為什麼
ours is but to do or die
只管拚命與犧牲
Semper Fi. Over
「永遠忠誠」完畢
Dear Joe, how the hell are you?
親愛的喬伊,你到底怎麼了?
Or, given that you're not much of a writer, should I not expect an answer?
因為你不愛寫信 就應該音訊全無嗎?
The newspapers say our boys are doing great
報上說,我軍戰果輝煌
But I don't think the reporters have been to Kaneohe Bay Hospital
但我想記者都沒看到 肯尼歐灣醫院的傷兵
I found a stray dog the other day on Waikiki
前幾天在瓦基基撿到只流浪狗
I gave him a bath and took him in
帶回家洗個澡留下來養
He reminded me of you - but cuter
它令我想起你,但它比較可愛
At least he keeps me warm at night
至少它晚上給我溫暖
I try not to think about you. About what might be happening over there
我盡量不想你 也不去想可能發生的事
But sometimes, when I'm lying in bed
但是,有時候躺在床上
I can't keep myself from wondering where you are
忍不住擔心你的處境
How you're doing
和過得好不好
What the hell you doin'?
你在幹嘛?
Writing a letter to my son
寫信給我兒子
Forget your orders? No letters out
你忘了命令?不准流出一個字
Command don't want postmarks going to the reservation
上面不准郵件進入保育區
Hey! You hear me?
沒聽到嗎?
I thought that he might read 'em when I get home
我回家後他就看得到啦
What's his name?
他叫什麼名字?
Your son
你兒子
It's George. George Washington
喬治,喬治華盛頓
George Washington Yahzee
喬治華盛頓亞吉
It's got a bit of a ring to it
聽起來蠻響亮的
My wife wasn't so sure
我太太不太喜歡
She's a little more traditional
她比較傳統
- Nice-looking family. - Let's see, Yahz
-好漂亮的一家人 -給我看看,亞吉
Yeah, that George, he's quite a character. He's got a mind of his own
喬治很有個性 他有自己的想法
Can I try one of those?
我可以抽一根嗎?
- You smoke? - Not really
-你抽煙? -抽著玩的
- Dismount! - Get out of the truck!
-下來! -快下車!
Let's go! Let's go!
動作快!
- Follow me! - Let's go!
-跟我來! -走!
- I'm hit! - Yahzee!
我中彈了!
Yahzee!
亞吉
Take it off! It burns!
拿下來!好燙!
You're not hit. Just shut up. You're not hit
你沒中彈,閉嘴!
- Spread out! - Move!
-散開! -動作快!
- Where the hell are they comin' from? - From us
-炸彈從哪來的? -我們自己人
- What? - They're not Jap guns
-什麼? -那不是日本人的炮
- We're getting shot at by our own guys? - We're supposed to be on road 04
-自己人炸自己人? -我們應該走四號路
- Get the regiment on the horn. - I can't!
-通知團部 -沒辦法!
- Tell 'em they're shelling¡­ - I can't! The radio's out. It's been hit
-告訴他們炸到自己人 -不行!無線電炸壞了
- They're firing too short! - The Japs gotta be way ahead of us
-他們炸太近了 -日本鬼子一定在我們前面
Do somethin'
想點辦法
Shit¡­ Follow me!
跟我來
- We're on the wrong fuckin' road! - Goddamn it!
-我們走錯路了 -干!
God
完蛋了!
Son of a bitch!
龜孫子
I got you, mac!
不要怕,老哥!
Corpsman!
救護兵!
Nellie!
奈!
You were right, Joe
你說的沒錯,喬伊
I do look like a Nip
我長得像日本人
What the hell are you talking about?
你在說什麼?
Putting on that Jap uniform.
穿上他們的制服
Trying to get one of their radios, call off our guns
用他們的無線電 通知我方停火
- That's stupid. - Shut up. Let him talk
-笨主意 -閉嘴,讓他說完
- He's not goin' out there. - You're not in charge here, Enders
-他不能出去 -這堣ㄔ悝A指揮,恩得斯
I got orders, Gunny. He's my responsibility!
我身負命令,吉尼 我要保護他
He's just a kid! You killed your own!
他還年輕啊! 你們在殺自己人!
What's wrong with you? You killed your own! Sons of bitches!
你們有毛病啊! 你們在殺自己人!王八蛋!
You killed your own!
你們在殺自己人!
- Sure you're up to this? - Find out soon enough, sir
-你確定要這麼做? -馬上就知道答案了,長官
- What the hell are you doin' there? - I'm goin' with him
-你想幹嘛? -我跟他去
If that's OK with you
如果你沒意見的話
Give me the rifle
槍給我
Horyo-da
戰俘
It's Jap for prisoner
「戰俘」的日本話
All right, everybody be ready
好啦,大家準備
Horyo-da!
戰俘
Now!
衝啊!
Hit me. Hit me
打我
Please don't hit me!
不要打我!
Yahzee!
亞吉
Kill him!
殺了他!
Goddamn it, kill him!
快點,殺了他!
Get on the radio!
去無線電那!
Bowie White, Bowie White, this is Carson Red!
白鮑威,這是紅卡森!
Cease fire! Cease fire! You're shelling marines!
停火!你們在炸自己人!
Sergeant!
中士!
Cease fire! Cease fire!
停火!
Add 325, fire for effect!
距離加325米,立刻射擊!
Redirect fire. Add 325, fire for effect
調整!加325米,立刻射擊!
Let's go!
走啦!
Crank it up! Let's go!
搖高點!快!
Commence fire!
開火!
Well, I'll be
奏效了
Colonel. Can I help you, sir?
請問什麼事,上校?
I'm looking for Sergeant Enders. Joseph F Enders
我想找一位恩得斯中士 約瑟夫恩得斯
Enders
恩得斯
Yes, sir
是的,長官
Report I read claims you went above and beyond
據報你非常神勇
Sir?
長官
You've been recommended for commendation
我們已推薦你接受表揚
And I concur. But I don't see any point in you having to wait around
我非常同意,但何必等待…
for all those formalities to work themselves out
繁複的公文往返
Not when I got one of these handy
我手邊正好有個勳章
Congratulations, Enders
恭喜,恩得斯
You saved a lot of marines
你救了不少同胞
I wasn't alone in that, sir. I couldn't have done it without Private Ben Yahzee
這不是我一個人的功勞,長官 多虧了二等兵班亞吉的幫忙
Oh¡­ Right. The, uh, Indian
對,那位印地安人
Begging the colonel's pardon, he's a Navajo, of the Bitter Water People
抱歉,他是納瓦荷人 母系苦水族
born for the Towering House clan
父系塔樓族
Of course. Navajo. Towering House clan
當然,納瓦荷人,塔樓族
You keep up the good work, Enders
繼續保持下去,恩得斯
Send that to Nellie's wife
把這個寄給奈堛漱茪
You ever not miss mailcall, Enders?
每次都有你的信,恩得斯
My mom says somebody takes the time to write a letter
我媽說,人家花時間寫信
you should read the letter
你該花時間好好讀
Does she let you drink, your mother?
你媽肯讓你喝酒嗎?
No. But she's not here
不肯,但她又不在這
- What is it? - Well, it ain't Chianti, I'll tell you that
-這是什麼酒? -確定不是法國紅酒
It's rice wine. It's Jap sake. But it does the trick
米酒類,是日本清酒 反正會醉就是了
How much of this crap do you have anyway?
你有多少這種東西?
You have a little trouble with that ear, don't you, Joe?
你這只耳朵有問題對不對?
Ah, real problem's the inner ear. It's anvils and stirrups and shit
問題在內耳,耳鼓耳膜之類的
I'm a little out of balance
我的平衡感不太好
You done good on that hill today, Yahzee
你在山丘上表現很好,亞吉
Yeah, I did, didn't I?
是啊,表現不錯吧?
I bet I surprised the shit out of you
一定嚇了你一跳
It was a noble thing that you did, Joe
你的情操很崇高,喬伊
To give your Silver Star to Nellie's wife
把銀星勳章給奈堛漱茪
I don't give a shit about medals
我才不在乎獎章
The first one they gave me¡­
他們給我的第一枚
I threw it into the ocean
被我扔到海堨h
What'd you get that one for?
那次是為了什麼事?
For not dyin'
因為我撐著沒死
The 15 men who fought with me got decorated too. For dying
15個戰友一起接受表揚 他們悉數陣亡
So¡­
所以…
Lieutenant was killed the night before and¡­
中尉前一晚就戰死了
none of the sergeants even made it out of the landing craft, so¡­
士官們也全死在登陸艇
that left me in charge. It was my first command
所以只好由我指揮 我第一次發號施令
Orders were to hold some shitty swamp marsh on the ass-end of nowhere
上面下令死守 某個鳥不拉屎的沼澤
And I did
我只好聽命行事
All of the men under my command¡­
我手下的弟兄
men who trusted me¡­
信任我的人
who begged me to pull back¡­
全都求我撤退
not one of them made it
結果沒有一個生還
Just one stupid asshole
除了一個固執的渾球
And for that, they gave me the Silver Star
他們因此給我銀星勳章
What were their names?
他們叫什麼名字?
It might be good to tell a story about 'em
說他們的故事
You know, who they were and what they were like
最好也知道他們的名字和長相
What a magical pile of Navajo horseshit. What the hell for?
納瓦荷人鳥規矩真多 要幹什麼?
To honor them
向他們致敬
Their memory
紀念他們
You know, it wasn't your fault, Joe. You were just followin' orders
那不是你的錯,喬伊 你是聽命行事
Yeah
是啊
I'm a good fuckin' marine
我是他媽的傑出陸戰隊
That's why they gave me this detail
所以派這個任務給我
Yeah
是喔
I'm a good fuckin' marine
我是他媽的傑出陸戰隊
- Joe! - What?
喬伊  怎麼
Goddamn you, Joe Enders!
你他媽的,喬伊恩得斯
Really
沒錯
It's all right
不要想太多
Come on, Joe. I got you
來,喬伊,我扶你
What the fuck?
幹什麼?
I ain't that drunk, Yahzee. You cut that horseshit out
我沒醉死,亞吉,別亂整
What's your expected arrival to the village? Over
什麼時候抵達村莊？
Around 1500. Aerial Reconnaissance reports
大約1500，空軍偵查報告
no movement, looks secure
沒有活動，好像蠻安全的
Request hot chow and mailif possible. Over
要求熱食與信件，完畢
I'm gonna mix my daddy's strawberries in this Swedish concoction called yoghurt
混合草莓與這瑞典玩意兒 就成了優酪乳
God willin', America will develop the taste
所幸美國人會自創口味
What about you, Charlie? What's life got in store for you after this mess?
戰後你想幹嘛,查理?
Sheep? As in Chick's girlfriend, sheep?
奇克拿來當女朋友的綿羊?
Charlie's family owns the biggest flock in the Four Corners area
查理家的羊群是四州最多的
No shit?
不是蓋的?
- You a rich man, Whitehorse? - We do OK
-你是富翁嘛,白馬 -還好啦
Taxis. A whole stinkin' fleet of 'em. That's how I'm making my millions
我要成立計程車隊 那是我致富的秘訣
And then I'm goin' back to the motherland
然後我要回到我的故鄉
I'm gonna build myself a villa on the cliffs of Santorini
在聖多里尼峭壁蓋棟別墅
Ah, Santorini, my friends - that's living
聖多里尼,哇,奢華
Sounds nice. What about you, Zee?
不錯,你呢,吉?
Thinkin' about teaching
我考慮去教書
Ah, teaching. Bring a little something back to the reservation?
引進新知識到保育區
Actually, more interested in bringing some of the reservation back to the world
事實上,是將保育區的知識 介紹給全世界
Hoping to teach college. American history
希望能到大學教美國歷史
Oh, that's just what we need
很符合我們的需要
Yahzee teachin' college boys about Custer's scalpin' at Little Bighorn
亞吉告訴大學生 卡司特怎麼在小彼弘被剝頭皮
And what about Kit Carson, and what they did to the Navajo in the Long Walk?
奇特卡森逼納瓦荷人 遷徙三千哩又怎麼說?
You ever read about that, Chick?
沒讀過吧,奇克?
Didn't think so
一定沒有
How about you, Joe?
你呢,喬伊?
- What? - What are you doin' after this mess?
-什麼? -戰後你想幹嘛?
It's gotta end sometime
戰爭總是會結束的
Dear Joe, we got great news today
親愛的喬伊,今天有個好消息
President Roosevelt announced the end of blackouts on Hawaii
羅斯福總統宣佈取消 夏威夷的燈火管制
We thought the day would never come
本以為遙遙無期
There's still a ten o'clock curfew, but it doesn't matter to me
10點仍有宵禁但影響不到我
After a 12-hour shift I'm too tired to do anything but write letters
值班12小時後 累得只有精力寫信
There is a real sense that the war is going well, and could be over soon
真正感覺到戰況不錯 戰爭隨時都有可能結束了
I think about you more and more. If you're alive or dead out there
越來越想你 你到底是死是活呢?
I check the mailevery day, knowing there's going to be an answer
我每天查信 心想遲早會有答案
Are you reading these, Joe?
你有收到我的信嗎,喬伊?
Are you listening?
聽到我的話嗎?
- We're secure on the left side. - Area's secured
-左翼沒有危險 -這區沒有危險
Set up defense positions
做好防禦工事
Chick, bed 'em down for the night
奇克,負責紮營
Harri
哈利
What's wrong?
怎麼回事？
I'm hurting
好痛
Here's some pain reliever
這埵釣リ豯h藥
Don't worry, you'll be fine
別擔心，你沒事
Thank you, Uncle
謝謝，大叔
That's startin' to sound like something
聽起來蠻有感覺的
I didn't know you were an artist
不曉得你是個藝術家
Oh, it's stupid
隨便塗鴉
It's just something I would do as a kid on my grandmother's kitchen table
小時候常在祖母廚房桌上畫
Well, it's nice
很不錯
You Catholic?
你信天主教?
I used to be
以前啦
I was thinkin' about when they confirmed me
正好想起受堅信禮的事
I was eight, and they anointed me with the holy water
八歲那年,他們幫我抹聖水
And I remember¡­
我還記得
they told me I was a soldier of Christ
他們說我是基督的戰士
I guess somewhere along the way I must have switched units
不曉得什麼時候迷失了自己
It's oil
是油
They don't use holy water to confirm. They use oil
堅信禮不用水,是用油
I was raised Catholic too
我家也信天主教
Mission school on the reservation
上保育區內的教會學校
It's funny. Fathers didn't like us talking Navajo at Mass
神父作彌撒時 不喜歡我們說納瓦荷語
Of course, one Sunday I forgot
有個禮拜天我忘記了
They punished me by tying me to the radiator in the basement
被處罰綁在地下室的暖爐上
For two days
整整兩天
I think I was eight too
記得我當時也是八歲
Well, they're sure lettin' you talk Navajo now. Yeah
現在可以自由說納瓦荷語了
You know, when this is over, maybe you should come out to Navajo country
戰爭結束後 或許你該來看看納瓦荷村
Monument Valley is a beautiful place. It's peaceful
紀念碑河谷很美,很幽靜
You know, we could do some things that you don't do in the Corps
可以嘗試軍隊堥S有的東西
Like ride horses, eat fry bread, do some hunting¡­
比如騎馬,吃炸麵包,打獵
Horses
騎馬
I don't know. It's a pretty long drive to Arizona
再說啦 到亞歷桑那有好長一段路
But it might be worth it. You know, you could meet my son
很值得,你可以看看我兒子
And he could meet Joe Enders
他也可以見見喬伊恩得斯
the guy who watched over Daddy's scrawny ass
保護他瘦弱老爸的恩人
You must be a very good father, Ben
你一定是個好父親,班
Ben. You know, you've never called me that before
班?你以前不曾這樣叫我
Enders. What kind of name is that anyway?
恩得斯是哪一國名字?
It's Italian. Used to be Endrolfini before some asshole at Ellis Island got hold of it
意大利,原本叫恩卓菲尼 被艾利斯島移民局簡化了
Captain needs to code a message back to command post
上尉要發一封密碼信到司令部
You the Indian?
你就是那個印地安人?
Yeah, I'm the Indian
是的,我是那個印地安人
It's just a few minutes' drive. We'll get you back in no time
只要幾分鐘,馬上送你回來
- I need to speak with you, Gunny. - Yeah. Give me a second
-我有話跟你說,吉尼 -等我一下
Got this with the mailtoday. You ever had pickled herring?
今天寄來的,吃過醃鯡魚嗎?
I need out
我想調職
What the hell are you talkin' about?
你在說什麼?
This detail
目前的職務
My duty
我的任務
I can't do it
我無法執行
Well, I need you, Enders
我需要你,恩得斯
Yeah. You've been saving a lot of marines
你救過很多同胞的命
I'm requesting mast with battalion commander. I want out
我要向營部司令申訴 我要調職
Oh, yeah? You and me and every other mother's son. We all want out
是嗎?大家都是媽媽的兒子 誰不想調職
Well, as long as there's a Tojo and a Hitler out there
只要東條英機和希特勒不死
we have to keep on fighting. Is that understood?
我們就得繼續戰,懂嗎?
- You're not hearing me. - I'm hearing you just fine
-你誤會了 -我聽得一清二楚
Now, there's a war goin' on worldwide
現在全世界都在打仗
and it ain't bein' waged on your wants and wishes
沒空理會你的需求和願望
Now you get some sack time. That's an order
好好去睡一覺,這是命令
Goddamn it! I can't do it!
去你的!我下不了手!
I can't perform my duty!
我無法執行任務!
Hey there, sweetheart
嘿,小朋友
Hi. It's OK
嗨,沒有關係
You don't have to cry. You're gonna be all right
不要哭,不會有事
Got a present for you
我送你一個禮物
This is chocolate
巧克力
You see, you eat it¡­ and it's good
吃吃看,很好吃
It's good
很好吃
You want some?
要不要嘗嘗看?
You'll have to chew it next time. Here
下次記得先嚼一嚼
Harrigan, go!
哈利根,走!
Incoming!
炸彈過來了!
Run!
跑!
Go! Run!
走!快跑!
Harrigan! Make her run!
哈利根!叫她跑!
Come on! To me!
快點!來這邊!
Harrigan!
哈利根!
Come on, keep moving!
該走了!
Fall back!
退回來!
Help! Help!
求救!求救!
I can't let 'em take us
不能讓他們活捉我們
What are you talking about?
說什麼呀?
Don't kill him
留他活口
He's important
他很重要
We need to interrogate him
我們需要拷問他
Enders!
恩得斯
I can't find Ox or Whitehorse
我找不到公牛和白馬
Have you seen them?
你有看到他們嗎?
He's over there
他在那
Oh, shit¡­
噢,天啊
This was supposed to be a secured area! What happened?
這堣ㄛO應該很安全嗎? 怎麼回事?
I killed him
我殺了他
You¡­ you what?
你什麼?
I took my grenade and¡­ and I threw it and I blew him up
我用手榴彈 丟過去把他炸個粉碎
What the hell is wrong with you?
你他媽的瘋了!
Yahzee!
亞吉
Yahzee! Yahzee, no!
亞吉,不要!
Get up!
起來!
Come on. You can do it
來呀,動手啊
- Yahzee. - Let him go
放過他
Yahzee, no
亞吉,不要
Go on. Why can't¡­ Come on. Do it
為何不…動手啊!
- Do it! - No
-動手啊! -不
We heard about Whitehorse, Yahzee. We shall honor his name and his memory
我們聽說白馬的事了，亞吉 我們會表揚他的功績
Farewell, Charlie, farewell
再會，查理再會
Yes, Charlie, farewell
是的，查理再會
You know, Whitehorse¡­ he saved my bacon
你知道,白馬…救過我一命
Wonder what George Armstrong Custer would make of that
不知道喬治卡斯特會怎麼想
I remember my granddaddy sittin' on the porch talkin' about huntin' Indians
記得祖父以前坐在廊下 講獵印地安人的事
like he was talkin' about gophers or somethin'
講得簡直像獵地鼠一般
About gettin' paid three dollars per Comanche ear
獵一個賺三塊美金
I know. Gets you thinkin'
我知道很難想像
Another 50 years, who knows, we could be sittin' down with the Nipponese
再過50年,或許我們 跟日本人會變成朋友
Drinkin' their sake, shootin' the shit¡­
喝著清酒,隨意哈拉
lookin' for somebody else's ass to kick
聊看看還可以打誰
You think too much
你想太多了
First time I ever been accused of that
第一次有人這樣稱讚我
Thought I told you not to go traipsing around on your own
告訴過你別一個人到處晃
You know, Charlie blessed my son in the Navajo way the day he was born
你知道,查理祝福過我兒子 出生時,以納瓦荷傳統方式
He wondered about cowboys watching Indians' backs
他曾懷疑老美會保護我們
Something about it didn't seem right
老是感覺不對勁
I thought it was Charlie just being Charlie
我覺得查理只是多心
He didn't even want to come to this damn war. I talked him into it
他其實一點都不想來打仗 是我說服他的
Maybe you made a mistake
或許你錯了
Maybe we all did
大家可能都錯了
I was following orders, Ben
我只是奉命行事,班
My orders were to protect the code
我奉命保護密碼
If one of you got caught, talked, the code would be useless
如果你們其中一人被捕 一旦洩密,密碼就沒用了
I was following orders, Ben
我只是奉命行事,班
Course you were, Joe. You're a damn good fuckin' marine
當然是,喬伊 你是他媽的傑出軍人
The Viking wants to see you
海盜要找你
He says right away
他說馬上
I want you to brief everybody, make clear what's happenin'
跟大伙說明一下怎麼回事
All right. Got no problem with point, Gunny
我打頭陣沒問題,吉尼
- You wanted to see me?
你找我？
Yeah
恩
The 8th is moving out already and we need to be ahead of 'em
第八營已經出發了 我們要迎頭趕上,領先他們
The destination is that big piece of rock you see over there
目標是那邊那塊巨石
The last defensible ridge on this island
這個島的最後防禦據點
Now, thinkin' is, we take the mount, Saipan is pretty much ours
攻下那山頭 塞班幾乎就是我們的了
Yesterday, bombers beat the shit out of that rock
昨天轟炸機 把山頭炸得差不多了
The brass is nervous. They expected more resistance over there
上面很緊張,可能遭到頑抗
Now they want us to go over and check it out
要我們過去查看一下
So where the hell they got us now?
他們要我們去哪?
Goin' up the mountain
翻上山頭
Have ourselves a little peek
偷窺一下
That codetalker is out front for a reason
要密碼戰士打頭陣是有原因的
That's exactly where I need him to be
他正好派上用場
If there's still a problem between the two of you
假如你倆之間有嫌隙
I would like to straighten that out, right here, right now
最好現在立刻擺平
- No problem here, Gunny. - That's good
-我沒事的,吉尼 -好極了
But there's still one here
但我還有一個問題
You just do what you're supposed to do, Sergeant
你只須做你該做的事
Nothing more, nothing less
不多也不少
Enders
恩得斯
You got another letter
恩得斯,又一封你的信
Freeze!
不要動!
Jesus Christ! We're in the middle of a goddamn minefield!
要命!我們站在地雷區中央!
Chick's gonna get us out. Right, Chick?
奇克會帶我們脫離的,是吧?
Sure I am
當然
One line after Chick
跟著奇克排一縱隊
Pappas
帕帕斯
Move, Greek
走呀,希臘人
I'm gonna get my fuckin' balls blown off out here!
我的蛋蛋會被炸個粉碎!
Yahzee! Stop!
亞吉,站住!
Move out!
躲開!
Yahzee!
亞吉
Nice shootin', Pap
射得好,帕帕斯
The 8th's movin' in. We'd better check out the other side
第八營進來了,查看另一邊
Got it. You all right?
瞭解,你還好吧?
Chick, take the left flank. Enders, go right. We'll cover you with a 30
奇克負責左翼,恩得斯到右翼 我們會用榴彈炮掩護你們
- On it. - All right?
-就位 -好了嗎?
OK, let's go!
好,走吧!
Move!
出發!
Hjelmstad!
賀瑪斯德!
- Help him up! - Gunny!
-快幫他! -吉尼!
Come on. Come on
快
- Christ. - Joe! Joe!
-天啊 -喬伊!
Tear him open
撕開衣服
You want morphine?
要來點嗎啡嗎?
- You want morphine? - Yeah
-要來點嗎啡嗎? -好
You'll be all right, sir
你不會有事的,長官
Goddamn it, Yahzee, get over here!
可惡!亞吉,過來!
Fuck!
干!
Chick¡­ Stay with him
奇克,看著他
I got ya
有我在
I told you to stay with Gunny
我叫你照顧吉尼
Gunny's gone
吉尼掛了
We're not gonna make it out of here, are we, Joe?
我們出不去了,對不對?
I'm runnin' out of ammo here, Joe
我快沒彈藥了,喬伊
I don't wanna die in this shithole
我不想死在這糞坑
You're not gonna die
你不會死的
Nobody else is gonna die
不會有人死的
We're gonna make it. We're gonna make it out of here
我們會活著 我們會活著出去
8th's caught out in the open. We gotta call in the flyboys
第八營被困在空地 我們必須請求空中支援
I'm gonna get that radio. Cover me
我去拿那個無線電,掩護我
He got the radio, Yahzee!
無線電被他拿走了,亞吉!
Cover me! I'm going!
掩護我,我去了!
Stay back!
退回去!
Fuckers!
王八蛋!
It won't bring your friends back
救不回你朋友的
What do you know about friends?
你懂什麼叫朋友?
Get us some air support!
快呼叫空中支援
Bowie White, this is Carson Red, Arizona
白鮑威,紅卡森呼叫 亞歷桑那
I say again, Carson Red, Arizona
重複,紅卡森呼叫,亞歷桑那
Coordinates!
指示座標!
Two-twenty, Mike, three-six
2-20,麥克,36
All right, let's go
好,走吧
We're gonna make it outta here
我們要殺出重圍
Damn it, Joe
可惡,喬伊
Just get it over with
快點動手
Shut up, Ben
閉嘴,班
Do it, Joe
動手,喬伊
Do it!
動手啊!
No one else is gonna die, Ben
不能再死人了,班
No one else is dying
不會再有人送命了
Joe, we did it
喬伊,我們成功了
God¡­
老天…
God!
老天
Oh, God¡­ Oh, Joe¡­
老天 哦，喬伊
We saved a lot of marines today
我們今天救了不少海陸弟兄
Yeah, we did, Ben
是啊,班
Charlie¡­
查理…
You know I didn't want to
你知道我不想殺他的
Right?
對吧?
Hail¡­ HailMary¡­
聖母瑪麗亞
full of grace¡­
萬福
our¡­
天…
our Lord is with thee¡­
天主與你同在
Holy Mary, mother of God¡­
聖母瑪麗亞,上帝之母
pray for us¡­
保佑我們
I got the last of 'em, Joe
我幹掉最後一個了,喬伊
His name was Joe Enders¡­
他名叫喬伊恩得斯
from South Philadelphia
南費城人
He was a fierce warrior
他是個英勇的戰士
A good marine
是優秀海軍陸戰隊
If you ever tell a story about him, George¡­
如果你要說他的故事,喬治
say he was my friend
就說他是我的朋友
The Navajo Code was vital in the victory at Saipan and every major battle in the Pacific
「納瓦荷密碼是塞班勝利的關鍵 太平洋區主要戰役也靠它」
It was never broken
這套密碼始終未被破解」